Perry Frank Johnson collection of railroad photographs
Center for Railroad Photography & Art
Perry Frank Johnson collection of railroad photographs
1939-1963
1947-1956
Center for Railroad Photography & Art
Johnson, Perry Frank
Several photographs in the collection were not shot by Perry Frank Johnson. Additional photographers include: Able, Charles; Baringer, Don; Bauer, Allen; Beaver, Edward; Carter, Jim; Goessi, O.; Lucy, Leonard; Maddock, D. L.; McCarter, Malcolm; Ross, Donald; Stevenson, W. J.
2009.1
3 linear feet 14 archival binders About 5,000 images including photographs and black-and-white prints.
This collefction is composed of photographic images shot by Perry Frank Johnson (1913-2007). The bulk of the collection was photographed by Johnson, but it also includes items he collected from other rail photographers. Images in the collection depict American railroads, mainly located in Indiana, Illinois, and Ohio.
Selected Search Terms
Countries
Belgium; Canada; France; Germany; United States
States/Provinces
Arkansas; British Columbia (Canada); California; Colorado; District of Columbia; Illinois; Indiana; Iowa; Kentucky; Louisiana; Maryland; Minnesota; New Jersey; Nova Scotia (Canada); Ohio; Ontario (Canada); Pennsylvania; Texas; Washington; West Virginia; Wisconsin
Railroads
Akron, Canton and Youngstown Railroad; Aliquippa and Southern Railroad; Androscoggin and Kennebec Railroad; Atchison, Topeka and Santa Fe Railway; Atlantic City Rail Line; Atlantic Coast Line Railroad; Baltimore and Ohio Railroad; Bangor and Aroostook Railroad; Belt Railway Company of Chicago; Bessemer and Lake Erie Railroad; Boston and Maine Railroad; Burlington Northern and Santa Fe Railway; Cambria and Indiana Railroad; Canadian National Railway; Canadian Pacific Railroad; Chesapeake and Ohio Railway; Chicago Aurora and Elgin Railroad; Chicago, Burlington and QUincy Railroad; Chicago and Eastern Illinois Railroad; Chicago Great Western Railway; Chicago and Illinois Midland Railroad; Chicago and Illinois Western Railroad; Chicago, Indianapolis and Louisville Railway; Chicago, Milwaukee, St. Paul and Pacific Railroad; Chicago and North Western Railway; Chicago, Rock Island and Pacific Railroad; Chicago South Shore and South Bend Railroad; Chicago Terminal Railroad; Chicago Transit Authority; Cleveland Transit System; Clinchfield Railroad; Columbus and Greenville Railway; CSX Railroad; Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad; Denver and Rio Grande Western Railroad; Des Moines Gary Railway; Detroit, Toledo and Ironton Railroad; Elgin, Joliet and Eastern Railway; Erie Railroad; Grand Trunk Western Railroad; Great Northern Railroad; Green Bay and Western Railroad; Gulf, Mobile and Ohio Railroad; Illinois Central Railroad; Illinois Terminal Railroad; Indiana Harbor Belt Railroad; Kansas City Southern Railway; Lafayette Street Railway; Lake Erie and Western Railroad; Lake Shore Electric Railway; Lake Superior and Ishpeming Railroad; Lehigh Valley Transit Company; Louisville and Nashville Railroad; Michigan Central Railroad; Middle Fork Railroad; Milwaukee Electric Railway Company; Minneapolis and St. Louis Railway; Minneapolis, St. Paul and Sault Ste. Marie Railroad; Missouri Pacific Railroad; Monon Railroad; Montour Railroad; Nashville, Chattanooga and St. Louis Railway; New York Central Railroad; New York, Chicago and St. Louis Railroad; New York, New Haven and Hartford Railroad; Norfolk Southern Railway; Northern Pacific Railway; Peoria and Eastern Railway; Pere Marquette Railway; Pennsylvania Railroad; Pittsburgh and Lake Erie Railroad; Pittsburgh Railways; Pittsburgh and West Virginia Railway; Reading Railroad; Rio Grande Southern Railroad; Shaker Heights Rapid Transit; Sierra Railroad Company; Southern Pacific Railroad; Texas and Pacific Railway; Toledo and Ohio Central Railway; Toledo Terminal Railroad; Toronto, Hamilton and Buffalo Railway; Union Pacific Railroad; Union Traction Company; Virginian Railway; Wabash Railroad; Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority; Western Pacific Railroad; West Side Lumber Company Railway; Yosemite Valley Railroad; Yreka Western Railroad
Subjects
Photography of railroads; Railroads--Pictorial works
Biographical Note
Perry Frank Johnson (1913-2007) was born to Lawrence and Myrtle Johnson on December 22, 1913, in Wellington, Ontario, Canada. The family later moved to the United States. Johnson spent his boyhood in Fort Wayne, Indiana, and began watching trains along the Nickel Plate Railroad in second grade. When he was older, he hiked to view trains along the Nickel Plate, Pennsylvania, and Wabash lines. In the late 1930s, Johnson moved to Franklin, Indiana, to pursue a bachelor's degree in biology at Franklin College.
In the Spring of 1942, Johnson's wife, Dorthea Nance Johnson (1916-2013), first encouraged him to photograph trains by shooting a few train photographs of her own. Then, World War II and Army service at the headquarters of an armored division in Europe intervened from 1942 through 1945. But, once he was back home in the United States, on March 1, 1946, Johnson finally began his years-long rail-photography avocation, writing, "One has to start somewhere if he is to take action pictures of railroad subjects, and after putting it off for a while I started here–on 11th St. in Michigan City, Indiana," where he was working for the YMCA.
In 1948, the Johnsons moved to Elyria, Ohio. From 1948 to 1961, Johnson was employed as the YMCA Boy's Work Director and ran Camp Iss-See-Kes Nature Museum each summer. Dorthea Johnson, meanwhile, began teaching first grade in 1955, and completed an MA in Education in 1957. She would go on nto serve as Principal at Maplewood School in 1962. Around the same time, Johnson joined the new Lorain County Metro Parks System as their first naturalist–he would later become chief naturalist when the department expanded. His job included eidting the department's newsletter, "Arrowhead," and photographing the parks. Perry helped design the Wildlife Observation Center Area in the Carlisle Visiting Center. The Park system named the visitors center at the Sandy Ridge Reservation the Perry F. Johnson Wetlands Center. Johnson retired in 1984.
Johnson shot the majority of his railroad photographs during the 1940s and 1950s. First, largely in northern Indiana, in and around Michigan City, and later, in northeastern Ohio, in and around Elyria, after the Johnsons relocated in 1948. Johnson printed and mounted his photographs in serveral albums–the early ones include Johnson's own typewritten descriptions of each image. He would later abandon this habit, however. When capturing subjefcts, Johnson did not discriminate among steam, electric, and diesel locomotives. He shot what he saw locally, sometimes with people in the images.
In retirement, Johnson led bird walks in Cascade Park for many years, and he was oneo f the founding members of the Elyria Audubon Society. He served many terms as President of the Black River Auducon Society, and he edited the Societys newsletter, "Wingtips." Perry passed away in 2007 and in 2009, Dorthea Johnson donated his railroad materials to the Center for Railroad Photography and Art.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains photographic material created by Perry Frank Johnson (1913-2007). The bulk of the collection consists of 4,912 black and white photographs shot primarily between 1947 and 1956 that depict portrait and action shots of locomotives near Johnson's residences in Michigan City, Indiana, and Elyria, Ohio. Other photographic material in the collection includes a small selection railroad images that Johnson collected or traded with other photographers. Several of these images depict railroad operations in Western Europe near the end of World War II in Manheim and Darmstadt, Germany; Brussels, Belgium, and Versailles, France. The collection images were originally bound in several scrapbooks.
Arrangement of the Collection
Collection maintains arrangement of the photographs' creator, Perry Frank Johnson, 1913-2007.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Donated by Dorthea Nance Johnson (1916-2013) in 2009.
© 2016, Center for Railroad Photograph & Art
Digitized Versions Available
Selected photographs are publicly available on the Center's website and Flickr account.
Related CRP&A Publications
Lothes, Scott, ed. Significant Images of Railroading. Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 2016.
- 1946-1947, Johnson-01; 240 black-and-white photographs (Binder Binder 1, Pages 001-100)
  Railroads
  Indiana, Chicago and Eastern Illinois Railroad; Chicago, Indianapolis, and Louisville Railway; Chicago South Shore and South Bend Railroad; Grand Trunk Western Railroad; Michigan Central Railroad; Monon Railroad; New York Central Railroad; New York, Chicago, and St. Louis Railroad; Pere Marquette Railway; Wabash Railroad
- 1946-1947, Johnson-02; 157 black-and-white photographs (Binder Binder 2, Pages 001-079)
  Indiana Boston and Maine Railroad; Chicago, Indianapolis, and Louisville Railway; Chicago South Shore and South Bend Railroad; Monon Railroad; New York Central Railroad; New York, Chicago and St. Louis Railroad; New York, New Haven and Hartford Railroad; Pere Marquette Railway
- 1946-1948, Johnson-03; 257 black-and-white photographs (Binder Binder 3, Pages 001-134)
  States/Provinces
  Illinois; Indiana; Ohio
  Chicago Aurora and Elgin Railroad; Chicago, Indianapolis, and Louisville Railway; Chicago and North Western Railway; Chicago South Shore and South Bend Railroad; Chicago Terminal Railroad; Erie Railroad; Illinois Central Railroad; Indiana Harbor Belt Railroad; Norfolk Southern Railway; Pere Marquette Railway
- 1947-1960, Johnson-04; 308 black-and-white photographs (Binder Binder 4, Pages 001-103)
  Arkansas; California; Colorado; Illinois; Indiana; Kentucky; Louisiana; Minnesota; Ohio; Pennsylvania; West Virginia; Washington; Wisconsin
  Baltimore and Ohio Railroad; Chicago, Indianapolis and Louisville Railway; Chicago, South Shore and South Bend Railroad; Illinois Central Railroad; Indaiana Harbor Belt Railroad; Kansas City Southern Railway; Lake Superior and Ishpeming Railroad; Louisville and Nashville Railroad; Maine Central Railroad; Middle Fork Railroad; Minneapolis and St. Louis Railway; Minneapolis, St. Paul, and Sault Ste. Marie Railroad; Missouri Pacific Railroad; Monon Railroad; Montour Railroad; Nashville, Chattanooga and St. Louis Railway; New York Central; New York, Chicago and St. Louis Railroad; New York, New Haven, and Hartford Railroad; Norfolk and Western Railway; Northern Pacific Railway; Peoria and Eastern Railway; Pennsylvania Railroad; Pittsburgh and West Virginia Railway; Pittsburgh and Lake Erie Railroad
- 1941-1949, Johnson-05; 147 black-and-white photographs (Binder Binder 5, Pages 001-063)
  Illinois; Indiana; Ohio; Ontario (Canada)
  Baltimore and Ohio Railroad; Canadian Pacific Railway; Chicago and Eastern Illinois Railroad; Chicago, South Shore and South Bend Railway; Illinois Central Railroad; Indiana Harbor Belt Railroad; Lake Erie and Western Railroad; New York Central Railroad; New York, Chicago and St. Louis Railroad; Pennsylvania Railroad; Pere Marquette Railway; Wabash Railway
- 1946-1949, Johnson-06; 563 black-and-white photographs (Binder Binder 6, Pages 001-156)
  Indiana; Ohio
  Chicago, Indianapolis & Louisville Railroad; Chicago, South Shore and South Bend Railroad; Grand Trunk Western Railroad; Michigan Central Railroad; Monon Railroad; New York Central Railroad; Norfolk Southern Railway; Pere Marquette Railroad
- 1946-1959, Johnson-07; 790 black-and-white photographs (Binder Binder 7, Pages 001-175)
  British Columbia (Canada); California; Illinois; Indiana; Kentucky; Massachusetts; Michigan; Nova Scotia (Canada); Ohio; Ontario (Canada); Pennsylvania; Utah; Virginia; West Virginia; Wisconsin
  Akron, Canton and Younstwon Railroad; Aliquippa and Southern Railroad; Atchison, Topeka and Santa Fe Railway; Atlantic Coast Line Railroad; Baltimore and Ohio Railroad; Bangor and Aroostook Railroad; Belt Railway Company of Chicago; Bessemer and Lake Erie Railroad; Boston and Maine Railroad; Cambria and Indiana Railroad; Canadian National Railway; Canadian Pacific Railway; Chesapeake and Ohio Railway; Chicago and Eastern Illinois Railroad; Chicago and Illinois Western Railroad; Chicago and Illinois Midland Railroad; Chicago, Indianapolis, and Louisville Railway; Chicago and North Western Railway; Chicago South Shore and South Bend Railroad; Clinchfield Railroad; Columbus and Greenville Railway; New York Central Railroad
- 1950-1956, Johnson-08; 472 black-and-white photographs (Binder Binder 8, Pages 001-096)
  Michigan; New York; Ohio
  New York Central Railroad
- 1946-1961, Johnson-09; 330 black-and-white photographs (Binder Binder 9, Pages 001-104)
  Chicago, Indianapolis and Louisville Railroad; Chicago South Shore and South Bend Railroad; Grand Trunk Western Railroad; Illinois Central Railroad; Indiana Harbor Belt Railroad; Michigan Central Railroad; Monon Railroad; New York Central Railroad; New York, Chicago and St. Louis Railroad; Pennsylvania Railroad
- 1948-1963, Johnson-10; 355 black-and-white photographs (Binder Binder 10, Pages 001-096)
  California; Colorado; Florida; Idaho; Illinois; Indiana; Louisiana; Missouri; Nebraska; Ohio; Oregon; Pennsylvania; Texas; Washington
  Baltimore and Ohio Railroad; Burlington Northen and Santa Fe Railway; Chicago, Indianapolis and Louisville Railroad; CSX Railroad; Monon Railroad; New York Central Railroad; Reading Railroad; Rio Grande Southern; Sierra Railroad Company; Southern Pacififc Railroad; Texas and Pacific Railway; Toledo Terminal Railroad; Toronto, Hamilton and Buffalo Railway; Union Pacific Railroad; Virginian Railway; Western Pacific Railroad; West Side Lumber Company Railway; Yosemite Valley Railroad; Yreka Western Railroad
- 1948-1957, Johnson-11; 226 black-and-white photographs (Binder Binder 11, Pages 001-113)
  Indiana; Ohio; Pennsylvania
  Baltimore and Ohio Railroad; Canadian Pacific Railway; Chicago, Rock Island and Pacific Railroad; Chicago, South Shore and South Bend Railroad; Erie Railroad; New York Central Railroad; New York, Chicago and St. Louis Railroad
- 1947-1960, Johnson-12; 325 black-and-white photographs (Binder Binder 12, Pages 001-104)
  California; Colorado; Illinois; Indiana; New Jersey; New York; Ohio; Ontario (Canada); Ottawa (Canada); Pennsylvania; Utah; Washington; Wisconsin
  Baltimore and Ohio Railroad; Canadian National Railway; Chicago Aurora and Elgin Railroad; Chicago, Burlington and Quincy Railroad; Chicago Great Western Railway; Chicago, Indianapolis and Louisville Railway; Chicago, Milwaukee, St. Paul and Pacific Railroad; Chicago North Shore and Milwaukee Railroad; Chicago, Rock Island and Pacific Railroad; Chicago Transit Authority; Cleveland Transit System; CSX Transportation Company; Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad; Denver and Rio Grande Western Railroad; Detroit, Toledo and Ironton Railroad; Elgin, Joliet and Eastern Railway; Erie Railroad; Grand Trunk Western Railroad; Great Northern Railroad; Green Bay and Western Railroad; Gulf, Mobile, and Ohio Railroad; Michigan Central Railroad; Monon Railroad; New York, Chicago and St. Louis Railroad; New York Central Railroad; Norfolk Southern Railway; Toledo and Ohio Central Railway; Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority
- 1948-1962, Johnson-13; 253 black-and-white photographs (Binder Binder 13, Pages 001-128)
  Indiana; Ohio; Wisconsin
  Akron, Canton and Youngstown Railroad; Baltimore and Ohio Railroad; Chicago North Shore and Milwaukee Railroad; Chicago South Shore and South Bend Railroad; CSX Transportation; New York Central Railway; Norfolk Southern Railway; Pennsylvania Railroad
- 1939-1945, Johnson-14; 161 black-and-white photographs (Binder Binder 14, Pages 001-047)
  Countries
  Belgium; France; Germany; United States
  California; District of Columbia; Illinois; Indiana; Iowa; Maryland; Minnesota; New Jersey; Ohio; Pennsylvania; Texas; Wisconsin
  Androscoggin and Kennebec Railroad; Atlantic City Rail; Chicago Aurora and Elgin Railroad; Chicago, North Shore and Milwaukee Railroad; Chicago, South Shore and South Bend Railroad; Des Moines Gary Railway; Milwaukee Electric Railway Company; Illinois Terminal Railroad; Lafayette Street Railway; Lake Shore Electric Railway; Lehigh Valley Transit Company; Pittsburgh Railways; Shaker Heights Rapid Transit; Union Traction Company